<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nlphotonics.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://nlphotonics.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-09-30T21:17:45+00:00</updated><id>https://nlphotonics.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nonlinear Photonics</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Because I like it</title><link href="https://nlphotonics.github.io/blog/2024/rational/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Because I like it" /><published>2024-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nlphotonics.github.io/blog/2024/rational</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nlphotonics.github.io/blog/2024/rational/"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes tough decisions need to be made. For me, one of them is to choose in which field of science I would like to work, as a future PhD student, or even as my life-long career.</p>

<p>I find this question similar to the quest of meaning of life: “Why you want to devote yourself into this field, not the others?” Before asking that, you may ask yourself “Why I choose an academic career?” or “Why PhD?”. The answers to these questions may not be some rigorous reasoning, like what we see in mathematics, but something like “Because I like it” (Obviously you can not get a PhD position by saying this, you need to show your experience, but here I want to talk about persuading yourself, not others).</p>

<p>I like to call this kind of belief or motivation as cheating yourself. I think we need that. But the problem is: Sometimes it’s hard to really cheat yourself. I used to dream of finding the field of science that was most meaningful and interesting to me. I took many elective courses, went to all kinds of lectures, searched on the Internet, but in the end I still could not make the choice. However, I knew I had to move forward, even though there wasn’t a clear direction. You have to contribute something to this society, and then get the reward.</p>

<p>Maybe following the routine is a good idea to make decisions. We look back into our past and focus on what we already have, and then move towards the direction based on this established road. However, I would rather use my life to continue searching what I really like than pursue something which is unexciting to me. And so far I think I have found the clue. There is one field which gives me a completely different feeling of interest than any other fields I have seen.</p>

<p>To make a long passage short, I just want to give a quick conclusion: I decide to be rationally irrational about which road to choose. I can not persuade myself 100 percent, with evidence and logic. But I’m feeling good about my choice, and I want to take efforts to make it a right choice in the end, also I believe I have the motivation to help me overcome the failures. The rationality makes me move forward and contribute to outer world, while the irrationality gives me inner happiness. The quest of meaning leads me to the path of achieving my meaning of life, hopefully.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Be rationally irrational, or equivalently, cheat yourself.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can we change the rules of nature?</title><link href="https://nlphotonics.github.io/blog/2023/rules-of-nature/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can we change the rules of nature?" /><published>2023-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nlphotonics.github.io/blog/2023/rules-of-nature</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nlphotonics.github.io/blog/2023/rules-of-nature/"><![CDATA[<p>We live in a society based on many established rules. These rules are made by human and sometimes can be changed by human. The nature we live in is also governed by rules, for example, laws of physics. Therefore, we may ask a similar question: Can we change the rules of nature?</p>

<p>The answer is a definite no. Imagine we could change the rules of nature, for example, one day, we had some methods to make the gravitational constant 10 times larger between some masses. Then the fact that we could change the rule is also a rule of nature, just because we are a part of nature. Actually, the rule we thought we could change is just a subset (or limit) of a more general rule. We did not change that rule, we just discovered a more general and complete rule.</p>

<p>This gives some eternity to the laws (rules) of nature. And also, this gives me some satisfaction, because the laws I learn, and, maybe someday, discover, will not be overthrown by someone else. I’m not saying that I will never be wrong. I’m saying that the legitimacy of the existence of the laws is not determined by some powerful people. The only one that can judge us is the nature itself.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The answer is a definite no.]]></summary></entry></feed>